<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The glorie of the Lord arising, shaking terribly the earth, and overturning all, until righteousness be set up. Being an encounter with the ministers of the world touching their maintenance; wherein they are beaten with their own weapons, confuted by their own scriptures and arguments. Also, a testimony from the Lord against swearing. With a word to the heads of the nation, and to the judges of life and death. By those whom the world calls Quakers.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B03595</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G878</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E.733[6]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide 4152.f.21[3]</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99883427</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99883427</idno>
            <idno type="VID">183683</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B03595)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 183683)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; B1:4[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The glorie of the Lord arising, shaking terribly the earth, and overturning all, until righteousness be set up. Being an encounter with the ministers of the world touching their maintenance; wherein they are beaten with their own weapons, confuted by their own scriptures and arguments. Also, a testimony from the Lord against swearing. With a word to the heads of the nation, and to the judges of life and death. By those whom the world calls Quakers.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 21, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Giles Calvert, at the black Spread-eagle neer the west-end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "April. 15:".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church and state --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Oaths --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Quakers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:183683:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> THE GLORIE Of the LORD ARISING, Shaking terribly the EARTH, AND Overturning All, Until Righteouſneſs be ſet up.</p>
            <p>BEING An Encounter with the Miniſters of the world touching their Maintenance; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they are beaten with their own weapons, confuted by their own Scriptures and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments.</p>
            <p>ALSO, A Teſtimony from the Lord againſt SWEARING.</p>
            <p>With a Word to the Heads of the Nation, and to the Judges of Life and Death.</p>
            <p>By thoſe whom the world calls Quakers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> at the black Spread-eagle neer the Weſt-end of <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1654.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:183683:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:183683:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His thing was I moved of the Lord to write forth, which lay upon me, which is for the good of your ſouls, and for the good of all people, that you may ſee what ſpirit you act by: if by the ſpirit of Jeſus Chriſt, it leadeth into the and paths of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt; if not, the ſpirit of error, which lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth contrary to Chriſts doctrine; and if contrary to his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, minde and life, as it doth openly appear by the fruits of the doctrine of the world. The glory of the Lord ſhall ariſe, and his majeſtie, to ſhake terribly the earth, that your majeſtie, ye earthly ones, ſhall be laid in the duſt, and your glory and your renown: for the Lord hath brought forth, and will bring forth his <hi>Plant of renown,</hi> which makes the earth to ſhake ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribly, and that your loftineſs muſt be laid down, and the haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty people of the Land be weakned and grow feeble. The Lord hath ſpoken it, who will daſh in pieces, and will overturn all, until that righteouſneſs be ſet up, until the earthly part be ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: for in the earthly part there lodgeth his majeſty, and his glory, of the earthly mans, whom the god of the world blinds, and ſo they puſh one againſt another, and are blinde about the Law and Miniſtry, until the earthly part be thrown down.</p>
            <p>The Miniſters of the world are proud, that compel men to ſwear, to be without the doctrine of Chriſt, who ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all,</hi> though the Miniſters of the world have given the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſwear by, and the Rulers bring that for a witneſs, which witneſſeth againſt Swearing.</p>
            <p>The Miniſters of the world bring many Scriptures, and ſay, <hi>If we miniſter unto you ſpiritual things, it is the leaſt if you miniſter to us your carnal things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All Magiſtrates, I charge you in the preſence of the living Lord God of heaven and earth, Let Prieſts alone, as touching
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:183683:3"/> giving them their maintenance. You feed them fat, and make them idle; which the Scripture is againſt: which make ſo many of them ſeek after great benefits, and then they ſet the people one againſt another.</p>
            <p>Firſt, let them receive ſpiritual things, and miniſter them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they reap carnal things; not to reap carnal things, before they ſow ſpiritual things. Therefore buſie not your ſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them, but wait you in that which is pure, to receive the perfect Law of God, which is upon all ſinners and tranſgreſſors: which Law of God is perfect, according to that in the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: for, <hi>the law of God is perfect, and endures for ever;</hi> and ſo is that in the conſcience; and ſo for conſcience ſake, <hi>Let every ſoul be ſubject to the higher power:</hi> for if you have not received the Law from God, for conſcience ſake they ſuffer, (with your Law, which is contrary to that in the conſcience) and ſubmit to God, who is the Law-giver: and herein in all ages hath truth ſuffered, by them who had made Laws contrary to that in the conſcience.</p>
            <p>O let all Magiſtrates, Rulers, and People conſider, the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the world ſay they <hi>plowed in hope.</hi> Have they plowed all this while, ſome 30, ſome 40, ſome 50 yeers, and now loſt the end of their hope, and are now fain to ſeek to the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates for means? Oh horrible! Here they are contrary to the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>And they ſaid, <hi>He that planted a vineyard might eat of the fruit of it.</hi> O horrible and ſhameleſs vineyard-dreſſers! doth your vineyard bear you no fruit, who have been planting ſome 30, ſome 40, ſome 50 yeers, but you muſt now go a-begging with Petitions to Magiſtrates? This is contrary to Scripture: <hi>I have not ſeen the righteous forſaken, nor his ſeed begging their bread.</hi> All the vineyards you have dreſſed, bring forth nothing but briers and thorns. Such as you ſow, ſuch do you reap, and are fain to beg and ſeek to the Magiſtrates for means. Here you ſhew forth you are ſhameleſs vineyard-dreſſers, and have fruitleſs vineyards, as you do ſhew it, and you to be idle; and <hi>he that will not work, muſt not eat.</hi> Have you no fruit, but plowed in vain, and planted in vain, that all your trees are dry, and never a tree bears fruit? what husbandmen are you?</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:183683:3"/>
            <p> Another Scripture they bring: <hi>They that miniſter at the altar, are partakers of the altar.</hi> But this Scripture ſhames you: for your altar will not maintain you, but you ſeek to the Magiſtrates for means. So here you ſhame your altar, and ſhew you never ſowed ſpiritual things, but be them that ſow tares, and ſo are them that reap tares.</p>
            <p>Another Scripture you bring: you ſay, <hi>They that preach the Goſpel ſhould live of the Goſpel.</hi> This Scripture ſhames you again, and ſhews your Goſpel will not maintain you, but you ſeek to Magiſtrates: and the Miniſters of the Goſpel are aſhamed of ſuch a pack of Teachers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He that ploweth, ploweth in hope: he that threſheth, threſheth in hope, and ſhall be partaker of his hope.</hi> But theſe are <hi>Paul</hi>'s words, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 10. But how are the expectations and hopes of theſe men-teachers periſhed, that are fain now to ſeek to the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates for means, and put up Petitions to them? as there was a Petition put up lately to the Magiſtrates of <hi>England.</hi> How have they plowed in vain all this while, that no ſeed comes up<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Oh how have they loſt their hope! Oh how have they threſhed in hope all this while, and got forth no corn, but are fain to ſeek to the Magiſtrates for means and food! Theſe are they that have been beating the air, and threſhed in vain, and plowed in vain, and loſt their hope; who now cry to the Magiſtrates for means, and ſay they may not be left to carnal people, and their wives after them; and ſo judge the Churches to be carnal, which have been all this while ſowing, plowing, and threſhing it. O you ſhameleſs teachers! people have been led by you long.</p>
            <p>And in your Petition you ſay you propheſied in ſackcloth. O you lyers, here you have declared your ſelves lyers to all the Nation. Let all people take notice: when ever ſaw you a Prieſt in ſackcloth? Were not many of you the Kings Prophets, and Biſhops Prophets? And take away your Benefits, and you will be no Prophets. Have not you propheſied on a ſoft Cuſhion, and a hundred or two of pounds for it? But the light of God is ariſing, that people begin to ſee you to be falſe Prophets, and ſo deny you.</p>
            <p>And another Scripture you bring, <hi>The labourer is worthy of his hire;</hi> the workman is worthy of his meat. Wo unto him that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:183683:4"/> oppreſſeth the ſervant in his wages. That is the ſervant, and not the maſter: he that is learned may read.</p>
            <p>But how is it that Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> ſue men at the Law for means which they do no work for, nor are hired, and to them miniſter no ſpiritual things, but rail upon them? O how are theſe men worthy of their meat, which do no work? O how do theſe men take the Apoſtles words for a cloak to their idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs! How are theſe men bereaved of their ſenſe! And is not this unjuſt, and contrary to the Law, for a man that I have not hired, nor doth me any work, for to go to a Magiſtrate and fetch a Warrant, and ſue me at the Law, and ſtrain my goods, and bring the Scripture for his cloak, and tell me the workman is worthy of his meat, and the labourer worthy of his hire, when I neither hired him, nor ſet him to work? And here they are contrary to the Scripture, and contrary to the Law. O horrible, that ever ſuch ſhould take the Scriptures in their mouthes, which have been upheld by the Magiſtrates and Laws of the Nation: greedy ſhameleſs men, no Miniſters of Chriſt; which openly declares you to go for filthy lucre.</p>
            <p>Another Scripture you bring: <hi>Thou ſhalt not muzzle the mouth of the ox that treadeth out the corn,</hi> as ſaith the Law. O you ſhameleſs teachers, your mouthes muſt be muzled: have you been treading all this while, and no corn troden out to feed you, but are fain to ſeek to the Magiſtrate? The Apoſtle ſaith the Oxes mouth ſhould not be muzled that treadeth out corn: but here you ſhew that you have troden out no corn. O ye idle drones, have ye troden out no corn yet, but are the oxen and beaſts that are ſpoiling the corns, but you muſt ſeek to the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates; for you ſay the people are carnal. O ye fat bulls, no corn troden out yet? you have plowed in vain, you have ſowed in vain, your hope is in vain. Ye hypocrites, which now ſeek to the Magiſtrates for means, the Lord will open the Magiſtrates eyes to ſee you, which he hath done many.</p>
            <p>The Miniſters of the Goſpel ſaid, <hi>They that preached the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel lived of the Goſpel; they that plowed, plowed in hope; they that threſhed, threſhed in hope;</hi> and, <hi>The labourer is worthy of his meat.</hi> But you that will not work, muſt not eat: for they that labour are worthy of double honour, and the labourer is worthy of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:183683:4"/> his hire: but the Law ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt not put thy ſickle into thy neighbours corn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another Scripture the teachers of the world bring, where <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> he <hi>robbed other Churches for ſparing them,</hi> and had taken upon other Churches. But which of you teachers of the world have taken upon other Churches to ſpare your own where you are? but you ſue them at the Law, and ſeek to the Magiſtrates for means, if they will not give it you: and ſo caſt your ſelves out of the doctrine of Chriſt, and the Apoſtles, and the Churches.</p>
            <p>Another Scripture they bring againſt them that witneſs the new Covenant, which meet together in ſeveral houſes, or in the Fields or Commons, as they which gave forth the Scriptures did often; which is 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. and they ſay they <hi>creep into houſes, leading ſilly women captive, laden with ſin, and led away with divers luſts, ever learning, and never able to come to the truth; having the form, but not the power; muſt be turned away from.</hi> Let all take notice, if this Scripture turn not upon themſelves, who live in the luſt: who lives in headineſs, lives in the luſt, lives in cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs; lives in the luſt, and he leads into divers luſts. O ſuch have got the form, and have led this many hundred yeers, led ſome 30, ſome 40, ſome 60, ſome 80 yeers, and never able to come to the truth.</p>
            <p>All people take notice, <hi>The leaders of the people cauſe them to erre.</hi> And who have led captive all this while? Whether co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous men have not led, drunken men have not led, heady men have not led; proud, ſtrikers, fierce, deſpiſers do not lead yet? All people conſider whether people have not always been learning of ſuch which have the form, but not the power. They are to be turned away from. And ſuch as are ſtrikers and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious, ſuch you may ſee have led; and then they will bring that Scripture to maintain it, where the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Some preach Chriſt of envie, ſome of ſtrife, and ſome of contention.</hi> That was a time that few believed that was the Chriſt: the Apoſtle him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf did not, till it was revealed in him. But when his Name was ſpread abroad, and many had gotten the form, the Apoſtle bid them turn away from ſuch as had the form, but not the power: there he did not give liberty to hear envious men, nor
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:183683:5"/> vain contenders, but bids them turn away, and ſhun the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of vain contention: though the time was, he gave liberty to envious men, and contentious men, and men of ſtrife; that was the time of ſpreading his Name abroad: but when they had gotten the form, and not the power, then bids he all turn away from envious men, contentious men, and men of ſtrife.</p>
            <p>Another Scripture they bring, as <hi>Jude,</hi> to accuſe them that are ſeparated from the worlds Teachers, which turns upon themſelves, which <hi>go in the way of Cain, and after the errour of Balaam,</hi> who are <hi>ordained of old for condemnation.</hi> Let all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſee if they go not in the errour of <hi>Balaam, for gifts and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</hi> And whether the Teachers of the world be ſuch as were ſanctified by God the Father, and preſerved in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and which were to <hi>contend for the faith once delivered to the Saints.</hi> Let all take notice, if they be not ſuch as deny ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and deny perfection: and how do theſe contend for the faith, which deny it, and which deny the everlaſting Offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſt Jeſus?</p>
            <p>Another Scripture they do accuſe them with which witneſs the New Covenant, in <hi>Peter: Who through feigned words and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs make merchandiſe of the people,</hi> who are <hi>rioting and ſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in the day-time.</hi> Let all people take notice of this, if this do not turn upon them who are the teachers of the world, who are covetous, and make merchandiſe of the people; which were to come in the laſt times, which <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks of: and whether <hi>Peter</hi> was ſuch or no, who ſpake of them which ſhould come after him.</p>
            <p>Theſe Teachers of the world, who have told us of threſhing in hope, and plowing in hope, and have threſhed and plowed, yet have got nothing: and they have told us of a mediate Call, and their means was mediate. Now we believe it, and ſee it to be carnal: for mediate is carnal and natural; and <hi>the natural man knows not the things of God.</hi> And they have told us that the Steeple-houſe was the Church, and Sprinkling Infants was their Baptiſm, and a little bread and wine was their Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the Letter it was the Word, and the Letter it was the Light, and Hebrew, Greek, and Latine, was the Original, and the four books <hi>Matthew, Mark, Luke, and John,</hi> was the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:183683:5"/> and <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge</hi> were the two Well-heads of Divinity. And we ſee all this to be mediate means indeed, and mediate is carnal and natural; and <hi>the natural man cannot receive the things of God,</hi> as it is written. So we do teſtifie againſt all theſe, who have taught us this doctrine, to be no Miniſters of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>For we do witneſs now, the Miniſters of Chriſt, which are the Miniſters of the Word, which tell us God is the Word, Chriſt is the Light, the Church is in God, and the Baptiſm is with one Spirit into one body, and the Cup whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h the Saints drink was the blood of Chriſt, and the bread that the Saints break was the body of Chriſt, and the Saints fountain and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is God and Chriſt, and the Original is the Word: for <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late</hi> had the Original which the world hath, Hebrew, Greek, and Latine, who crucified Chriſt, as the world doth: and the world hath the four books, as the chief Prieſts had the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets words, which denied Chriſt the ſubſtance of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets; as the Prieſts which have the four books, deny Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus the ſubſtance now: ſo earth to earth. Light was before the world was, and the Word before the world was, and the Lamb of God before the world was, and the Fountain before <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge</hi> was, and the Word before Hebrew, Greek, and Latine was, and the Spirit before the invention of Infants Baptiſm was, which baptizeth into one body; and the Spirit was, in which the Communion is, before the table of devils was; which all Saints are made to drink into. Here are all you threſhers and plowers, with your mediate ſtuff, and mediate call, are all razed out in the full, and none come to the beginning, but are all blinde guides.</p>
            <p>All ye Heads and Rulers of <hi>England,</hi> who have a Law, and have made a Law to compel men and people to give their Tythes to the Prieſts: And if it be ſo, that the Prieſts muſt have the Tythes, let them act according to the Prieſts which did receive Tythes, which had a command to take Tythes, who had ſtore-houſes, that the ſtrangers, the fatherleſs, and widows thither were to come, to the ſtore-houſes, and be fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led within the Prieſts gates, that there might be <hi>no begger in Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:183683:6"/> Moſes,</hi> who was Judge of all <hi>Iſrael,</hi> gave forth this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, which he had received from God, which was in the firſt Covenant, a figure of the everlaſting Prieſt. So ye, if you now compel men to pay Tythes, and the tenth of their eſtates, let the Prieſts have Store-houſes, that all the fatherleſs, the ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and widows in <hi>England</hi> may thither come, and be ſatisfied within the Prieſts gates; and let them miniſter of that to them, that there may be no begger in <hi>England,</hi> as there was to be no begger in <hi>Iſrael.</hi> And ſo if you do thus, that the Prieſts have Store-houſes to put their Tythes and the tenth of mens eſtates in, to fill the ſtrangers, widows, and the fatherleſs, that there may be no begger in <hi>England;</hi> which if ye then act according to the figure, ye muſt not own Chriſt come in the fleſh, as we do, and that the Prieſthood is changed, &amp; the everlaſting high Prieſt witneſſed, over the houſhold of God; and therefore ſuffer we impriſonment, and our goods ſpoiling. And the Law is changed, and Jeſus Chriſt witneſſed the end of the Law, the end of the Prieſthood, who is the everlaſting Prieſt, where there is a trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure that filleth all, and to fill all; at whoſe name ſhall every knee bow, and every tongue confeſs him: for <hi>he hath enlightned every one that cometh into the world;</hi> though the one hate it, and the other love it, yet he that hates it, it ſhall make him confeſs, and let him ſee <hi>his deeds be evil,</hi> when he hath his reward: for <hi>lo, I come,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>and my reward is with me, to give to every one according to their works,</hi> whether they be good or evil: he ſaith ſo, who hath enlightned every one, and gives every one a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure according to their ability: he ſaith ſo, who is a King. Now the wicked and ſlothful ſervant, that hides his talent in the earth, from him it ſhall be taken, and he into utter darkneſs muſt go: he ſaith ſo, who is the Light of the world, and who hath given to every one a meaſure: and he ſaith ſo, whoſe grace hath appeared to all men, but <hi>teacheth us,</hi> ſay the Saints, <hi>to deny all ungodlineſs and worldly luſts;</hi> which the world, who lives in ungodlineſs and worldly luſts, <hi>turns into wantonneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="section">
               <p>THe word of the Lord to all your Maſters or Rulers of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, and Miſtreſſes: Rule in power, in love, in wiſdom, in patience, with the ſpirit of the living God; not with tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:183683:6"/> not with haſtineſs, not with your wills: for then that goes forth to rule for earthly ends; then you would have things ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to your own wills, which is contrary to that in the conſcience: and that rules not well, and that is croſs, and muſt be croſſed.</p>
               <p>And all you that are ſervants, labour in love, as unto God, for <hi>the earth is the Lords:</hi> not as unto men, but unto the Lord: for he that hath more of the earth then another, that makes the Maſter. And if you that are Maſters or Miſtreſſes do ſpeak to your ſervants, to that in their Conſcience, to guide them to the Lord, and to keep them in the fear of the Lord, to labor with love and ſingleneſs of heart, as unto God: If you that are Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters or Miſtreſſes be not guided by the Spirit of the Lord, but if the contrary nature go to reprove, it is as beating the air, and upon the earth, and it is to no purpoſe. But if you ſtand in the counſel of God, and be guided by the Spirit of the Lord, and ſpeak to the Spirit of God in others, you guide them up to God, to do what they do as unto the Lord. So when you are away, they are the ſame as when you are with them. And ſo the Juſt comes to rule in all; and he that rules, rules in love; and he that labours, labours in love, as unto the Lord. For, <hi>the earth is the Lords, and the fulneſs of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The time will come, that as with the ſervant, ſo with the Maſter; and as with the Miſtreſs, ſo with the maid. For all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one ſeed, and all the earth being the Lords: And here whatſoever is done, is done unto God, and not the ſervants of men, where the ſeed of God is redeemed out.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <p>CHriſt Jeſus ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all: not by heaven, for it is Gods throne; nor by the earth, for it is his footſtool; nor by Jeruſalem, for it is the city of the great King. Neither ſhalt thou ſwear by thy head: for thou canst not make one hair, white or black. But in all your communications, let your Yea be yea, and Nay nay: for whatſoever is more, comes of evil.</hi> Matth. 5. 34, 35, 36, 37.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:183683:7"/>
            <p> Though <hi>you have heard in the old time, Thou ſhalt not for ſwear thy ſelf, but perform the oath of the Lord;</hi> (Matth. 5. 33.) I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer: But now God hath brought forth his Son, the Oath of God, whom <hi>he ſwore by himſelf,</hi> (Heb. 7. 21.) as not finding a greater; who is the end of all Oathes, his Son, who ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if you do alleadge that <hi>Jacob</hi> ſwore <hi>by the fear of his father Iſaac,</hi> Gen. 31. 53. and <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſwore <hi>by the life of Pharaoh;</hi> Gen. 42. 15. I anſwer: Chriſt Jeſus the Oath of God, who ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all,</hi> reigns over the houſe of <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Joſeph.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if you do alledge that <hi>Moſes</hi> ſwore, who was a ſervant, I anſwer: but Chriſt is the Son, who ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all:</hi> and, <hi>This is my beloved Son,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>hear him.</hi> Luke 1. 33. Joh. 14. 9. Matth. 9. 7.</p>
            <p>And now if you do alledge that <hi>David</hi> ſwore, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20. 3. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 2. 22. I anſwer: Chriſt over him is King; <hi>David</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth it: who ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now if you do alledge that <hi>Solomon</hi> ſwore <hi>by the Lord,</hi> my anſwer is this, <hi>A greater then Solomon is here,</hi> (Luke 11. 31) which is the Son of God, who ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if you do alledge that <hi>Abraham</hi> ſwore, <hi>(Gen.</hi> 21. 24.) who ſaw the day of the Son; I anſwer: But when the Son came, he ſaid, <hi>Swear not at all;</hi> who was the Oath of God, which the Lord did perform in his Son, the everlaſting Oath. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. 21.</p>
            <p>And though this was in the old time <hi>an Oath to binde the ſoul, (Numb.</hi> 30. 2.) I anſwer: Chriſt Jeſus, the Oath of God, the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour of the ſoul, ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the Prophet ſaid, <hi>Every tongue ſhall ſwear,</hi> Iſa. 45. 23. I anſwer: Chriſt Jeſus, the Son of God, the end of the Prophets, ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God ſwore to <hi>David,</hi> that out of his loins, according to the fleſh, he would raiſe up Chriſt to ſit on his throne, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89. 49. I anſwer: He is the Oath of God, who ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all,</hi> who put an end to all Oathes.</p>
            <p>Though the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> did teach the people to <hi>ſwear by the Name of the Lord;</hi> (Jer. 4. 2.) I anſwer Chriſt Jeſus, the end of the Prophets, ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:183683:7"/>
            <p> Though they were then to binde them with an Oath to the Lord, as they had been bound with an Oath to <hi>Baal,</hi> ſo to bring them off that, to be bound with an Oath to the Lord, <hi>(Jer.</hi> 12. 16.) I anſwer: Chriſt Jeſus, the end of all bonds and oathes, ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And though <hi>Saul</hi> ſwore in the war, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19. 1. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer: Chriſt, who brings <hi>peace on earth, and good-will towards all men, (Luke</hi> 2. 14.) ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all:</hi> who ends war.</p>
            <p>And <hi>the Lord ſwore, and will not repent,</hi> (and <hi>becauſe he could ſwear by no greater, he ſwore by himſelf) Thou art a Prieſt for ever after the order of Melchizedeck;</hi> Heb. 7. 21, 24. who ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all;</hi> who is the Oath of God: and this man which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues for ever hath an unchangeable Prieſthood: and this man ſaid, <hi>Swear not at all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now if you do alledge that they ſwore in the old Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, <hi>(Levit.</hi> 5. 4.) I anſwer: Chriſt Jeſus, the new Covenant, ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if you do alledge that they ſwore in the Law; I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer: <hi>Chriſt is the end of the Law,</hi> Rom. 10. 4. and in the old Covenant they ſwore about earthly things, Oxen and Aſſes, and Sheep; but here they were not come to the doctrine of Chriſt, which is <hi>Yea and nay;</hi> who ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all; but in all your communications, let your Yea be yea, and your Nay nay: for whatſoever is more, is evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if you do alledge the Prieſt was to charge the woman with an Oath, <hi>Numb.</hi> 5. 19. I anſwer: Chriſt Jeſus the everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Prieſt, the Oath of God, <hi>(Heb.</hi> 7. 21.) who is come to put an end to all Oathes, who ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all.</hi> And his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, who were taught of him, who preached the Goſpel, and witneſſed the high-Prieſt, ſaid, <hi>My brethren, above all things, ſwear not at all: not by heaven, neither by earth, nor by any other Oath; but let your Yea be yea, and your Nay nay, leſt you fall into condemnation.</hi> Jam. 5. 12. Matth. 5.</p>
            <p>Now all you that ſwear, and bring to ſwearing, you are fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len into the condemnation, out of the doctrine of Chriſt, and by it you are condemned.</p>
            <p>Now if you do alledge in the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> that the Apoſtle ſaid, that <hi>men verily ſwore by the greater,</hi> and <hi>an Oath was the end of</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:183683:8"/> 
               <hi>controverſie and ſtrife amongſt men,</hi> Heb. 6. 6. I anſwer: This the Apoſtle brought as an example among men, as concerning God, who could not finde a greater, he ſwore by himſelf, concerning Chriſt his ſon; who ſaid, <hi>Thou art a Prieſt for ever after the order of Melchizedeck;</hi> who was made with an Oath. And where men are in ſtrife and controverſie, they are without, and have not learned the doctrine of Chriſt: for, as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>(Eph.</hi> 4. 20.) we have not learned Chriſt to live in ſtrife and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie: for it is out of <hi>Yea and Nay:</hi> and ſuch do oppoſe his doctrine; as to this day it is in <hi>England.</hi> A Judge did impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon one becauſe he could not ſwear, nor could deny the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Chriſt, but kept to <hi>Yea</hi> and <hi>Nay.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if you do alledge the Angel ſwore in the <hi>Revelation;</hi> I anſwer: The Lord God ſaith, <hi>I bring forth my firſt-begotten in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world, let all the Angels worſhip him,</hi> Heb. 1. 6, 8. who ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now you that would bring to ſwear, and do ſwear, becauſe the Angel ſwore, do worſhip the Angels, and are in the delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and do not hear the Son, <hi>(Mark</hi> 9. 7.) whom the Angels worſhip, who ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So though they ſwore in the old Covenant, Chriſt is the new, who ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all.</hi> And though they ſwore in the time of the Prophets, yet Chriſt is the end of the Prophets, who ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all.</hi> And though they ſwore in the family of <hi>Jacob,</hi> Chriſt reigns over the houſe of <hi>Jacob,</hi> who ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all.</hi> And if they ſwore in the time of the Prieſts, Chriſt Jeſus the everlaſting Prieſt, the Oath of God, ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all;</hi> who ſaith, <hi>In all your communications, let your Yea be yea, and your Nay nay.</hi> And the Goſpel is <hi>Yea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if you do alledge <hi>Moſes</hi> a ſervant of God ſwore, Chriſt the Son of God ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all.</hi> And if you do alledge that men ſwore; that was in ſtrife, and you bring them to ſwear to oppoſe the doctrine of Chriſt, who ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all; but in all your communications, let your Yea be yea, and your Nay nay.</hi> For they who are in ſtrife, have not learned Chriſt. And if you do alledge the Angels ſwore, all the Angels muſt worſhip the Son of God, the firſt begotten which is brought into the world; who ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:183683:8"/>
            <p> Now if you do alledge that <hi>Solomon</hi> ſwore; <hi>a greater then Solomon is here,</hi> who ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all.</hi> So the Son is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the Angels, the Son is above the Prophets, the Son is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the old Covenant, the Son is above <hi>Moſes,</hi> the Son is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove <hi>David,</hi> he calls him Lord; the Son is greater then <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon;</hi> the Son reigns over the houſe of <hi>Jacob;</hi> the Son is greater then all theſe, who ſaith, <hi>In all your communications, let your Yea be yea, and your Nay nay.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So having in theſe Northern parts for witneſſing forth the Son, who could not ſwear, ſo for the Truths ſake (and the Sons) that it might be ſet up, and not troden down, have I ſhewed forth, that you may all take warning how you ſwear, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand men to ſwear: for if you do, you draw from the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Chriſt, and you draw to evil and you draw into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, and you draw into the curſed ſpeaking, from <hi>Yea and Nay.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Chriſt Jeſus the Light of the world, who ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all: but in all your communications, let your Yea be yea, and your Nay nay,</hi> he hath <hi>enlightned every one that cometh into the world.</hi> Now every one loving this light, which Jeſus Chriſt hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned you withal, it will draw your mindes up to Chriſt, and teach you to <hi>know his doctrine,</hi> and how to walk in the truth: for this light in every one is according to Chriſts minde, who ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now all loving this light, never an Oath will be heard in the Land: for it will not let you ſwear, (but keep you to <hi>Yea and Nay)</hi> nor do no unrighteouſneſs. But all that hate this Light, you are ſwearers, and draw to ſwearing, and draw to oathes, and draw to unrighteouſneſs: and this Light of Chriſt is your condemnation: the Lord Jeſus hath ſpoken it. And to that in every one of your conſciences I do ſpeak, which ſhall eternally witneſs me, and condemn you that hate it: for to that I have cleared my conſcience.</p>
            <p>Capt. <hi>Morley,</hi> a Witneſs of the Truth, and for it, who ſuffered becauſe he could not ſwear, by Judge <hi>Packer,</hi> becauſe he could not deny Chriſts doctrine to ſwear.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:183683:9"/>
               <p> THe Word of the Lord to this Nation; to all you this is the Word of the Lord: to that in your conſciences do I ſpeak, whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h changeth not; but you change that act contrary to it; and all your Laws are changeable, that are made with that nature and minde, that act contrary to that in the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. Therefore to that in your conſciences am I moved to ſpeak, to the turning your minds to God, that you may wait to receive the Law from God, which law is according to that in every mans conſcience; and that no law be made againſt that in the conſcience. This am I moved of the Lord to command you, and charge you in the preſence of the Lord, and to minde the light in your conſcience, which teſtifies againſt all ſin, as doth the Law of God, which is perfect: and <hi>the Law was added becauſe of the tranſgreſſors, not made for the righteous.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore be awarned how you make Laws: for all muſt be cut down with the ſword of the Lord, which is contrary to that in the conſcience. And that no Law be laid upon Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: for the Law is for ſinners, and tranſgreſſors, and who abuſe themſelves with mankinde, and ſuch as defile the fleſh, and whoremongers, and adulterers, and murderers, and theevs, and all unrighteouſneſs, the Law of God which is perfect is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt; and ſo is that in the conſcience, which is of God.</p>
               <p>And ſee that your Laws be according to that in every mans conſcience: for the light in every mans conſcience is of God: That that in every mans conſcience may witneſs your Laws, elſe that in every mans conſcience will witneſs againſt your Laws not to be of God. And that muſt be hewn down with the Word of the Lord, as God hath done before in all Ages: for ſuch Laws perſecuted, priſoned, and crucified them who witneſſed for the teſtimony of a good conſcience: and ſuch did the Lord hew down, which were contrary to that in the conſcience; and their end was miſery, as in the generations you may read which are paſt, whoſe Law was contrary to that in the conſcience, which did not endure for ever; in which lodged all the Perſecution in all Ages. But the Law of God is perfect, according to that in the conſcience, and doth endure for ever. To that in your conſciences I do ſpeak, that you may
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:183683:9"/> wait upon God to receive it, leſt you be cut down, as they have been before you, which cut down the Saints with their Laws, under the name of Opinions and Sects.</p>
               <p>Therefore be awarned of making Laws, and that you have no Law concerning Religion, but let Religion defend it ſelf: for whatſoever is not of God, will not not ſtand, but will wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther away: but ſee that your Laws be according to that in the Conſcience, and then it will be againſt ſtrikers, and who abuſe themſelves with mankinde, to keep peace; and who defile their fleſh, and murderers, and whoremongers, and thieves, and adulterers; the Law which is equity, which is according to that in every mans Conſcience: for that is equity, which doth not reſpect any mans perſon: and that in the Conſcience is equity, and this ſhall ſtand for ever, when all inventions and imaginations will fall and ceaſe, and be caſt away from God, in the light which Chriſt hath enlightned every one with: in it is no Sect, no Hereſie, no Errour, no Opinion nor Blaſphemy: and to that do I ſpeak, which will eternally wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs me.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:183683:10"/>
            <head>To the Judges of Life and Death.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>TAke heed of putting any man or woman to death for Cattel or Money: for with the Law of God they were to be ſold for their Theft, if they had not where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to make reſtitution. So ſee that all your Laws be accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that in every ones Conſcience: for the Law of God is according to that in every ones Conſcience; that that in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ones Conſcience may witneſs your Law; elſe that in every ones conſcience will cry out againſt you and your Law, and witneſs the Law of God, which is perfect, according to that in every ones conſcience, and witneſs God to be the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver. And all Laws that are made and acted in the will of man, contrary to this light of Chriſt in the conſcience, are againſt Conſcience, and cannot ſtand, but God hath hew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them down, and will hew you all down, who act contrary to that in the conſcience. And ſee that no Law be acted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Religion: therefore take warning: to that in your conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences I ſpeak, which ſhall eternally witneſs me, (and ſhew you the judgement of God which hath paſſed before you up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the unjuſt, who have acted contrary to that in the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and have not received the Law from God) and condemn you that hate it, when the book of Conſcience is opened. To you this is the Word of God.</p>
            <p>Here have I let you know, and ſhewed you the Goſpel, that that in your conſcience may ſhew you when you act contrary to Chriſt, who ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all; but in all your communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, let your Yea be yea, and Nay nay: for whatſoever is more, is evil.</hi> And you that bring men to ſwear, you bring them into the evil. And, <hi>Swear not at all,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>leſt you fall into</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:183683:10"/> 
               <hi>condemnation.</hi> And you that ſwear, and bring others to ſwear, you are fallen into condemnation your ſelves, and draw others into condemnation, and out of the doctrine of Chriſt, and from the Goſpel, which is Yea and Nay in all your commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nications.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>To the Heads of England and other nations.</head>
            <p>TO all you Heads of <hi>England,</hi> and Nations elſewhere, which have a Law, and give it forth, that the Prieſts ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Tythes. <hi>Moſes</hi> the Judge of all <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Law from God, who gave forth orders to the People, and to the Heads, and to the Prieſts, which he had received from God: which Prieſts had a command to receive Tythes of the people, and of the brethren; and they had a Store<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, as in <hi>Mal.</hi> 3. <hi>Bring ye all the Tythes into the ſtore-houſe, that there may be meat in my houſe; and prove me now herewith, ſaith the Lord of hoſts, if I will not open the windows of heaven, and pour you out a bleſſing, that there ſhould not be room enough to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it.</hi> And all the ſtrangers, the fatherleſs, and the widows were to come within the Prieſts gates, that they might be fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and ſatisfied. Here was the wiſdom of God, that no beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger might be in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and no ſtranger might beg, nor no wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow might beg, nor no fatherleſs might beg, but come within the Prieſts gates, and be filled and ſatisfied, that the Lord thy God may bleſs thee, ſaith the Lord.</p>
            <p>And theſe Prieſts were a figure of the everlaſting Prieſt, and the Store-houſe of the everlaſting Treaſure Jeſus Chriſt: for when he was come and preached, the Apoſtles ſaid the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood was changed, which received Tythes; and he ſaid it was a changeable Prieſthood, and the Law was changed alſo: and he preached the unchangeable Prieſthood, and denyed the other that was changeable.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:183683:11"/>
            <p> Now all you Heads of <hi>England,</hi> who give forth a Law that men ſhould pay Tythes to the Prieſts: and them who witneſs Jeſus Chriſt the high Prieſt cannot pay Tythes for conſcience ſake: for the light in their conſcience brings them to witneſs Chriſt: and with your cruelty in your Law that you have made, it is to make them pay treble, and caſt them into priſon. Now if you do act according to the Scripture, that the Prieſts which received Tythes, as they did according to the Law, had a Store<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe to put their Tythes in, that all the ſtrangers in <hi>England,</hi> and all the fatherleſs in <hi>England,</hi> and all the widows in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> might come to the Store-houſe, and there to be filled with the Tythes, that no begger might be in <hi>England,</hi> no wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow to beg, no fatherleſs to beg, nor no ſtranger to beg. What a great deal of cumber would be taken out of the land? And the Prieſts ſhould miniſter it out to them: A figure of the everlaſting Prieſt which was to come, who miniſters out of the everlaſting treaſure Chriſt Jeſus. Now if you would do ſo, you might not own Chriſt come in the fleſh. So all you that hold up ſuch changeable Prieſts, and have not received your Law from God, as they did in the old time; Conſider what will become of you, that do oppreſs the poor people who witneſs the Goſpel, Jeſus Chriſt the end of the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and witneſs the new Teſtament, the end of the old Teſtament; and witneſs the new Covenant, the end of the old Covenant; and witneſs the Prieſthood which is not chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, but unchangeable, who miniſters out of the everlaſting treaſure; who was made with an Oath. And when the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable Prieſt was come, the Prieſthood that was change<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able was denyed. But theſe that are changeable are not made with an Oath: ſo we cannot hold up this Prieſthood that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Tythes now; nor we cannot own the Law that gives them Tythes. As for the Law and Command that God gave forth to <hi>Moſes,</hi> we own that, which was a figure of Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus which was to come; the unchangeable Prieſthood which the Apoſtles witneſſed and gave teſtimony to; and for witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him, they ſuffered their goods to be ſpoiled. And now in this Age, many ſuffer with a National Law, as at <hi>Lancaſter-</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:183683:11"/> Goal, which never ſuch a thing was read on in the Law of God, which was delivered to <hi>Moſes,</hi> that any ſuffered for not paying Tythes, or was to pay treble damages. Surely, ſurely, the cry for vengeance will be heard, which ariſes from the oppreſſed ſouls which lie under the altar.</p>
            <p>And the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> we own in its right place, a figure; but we cannot hold up theſe now, much leſs can we hold up this which God never commanded.</p>
            <p>They that did not bring the Tythes into the Store-houſe, they robbed God; and then there was not meat in their houſe, therefore he commanded them to bring them into the houſe, that there might be meat in the houſe; which was to fill the fatherleſs, ſtrangers, and widows. But now theſe Prieſts which are counterfeits, which take peoples Tythes with a Law which they have now from the Beaſt, that if any one will not pay them, they priſon them, and make them pay treble.</p>
            <p>And ſo theſe rob the poor people, and rob the fatherleſs, and the ſtrangers and widows, and do not fill them. So the cry is gone up to heaven againſt them, and many are almoſt made beggers by this oppreſſing Prieſthood; their cattel and their horſes taken away from them, and they caſt into priſon: and others are ſued at the Law by the Prieſt to pay treble damage: And ſuch are cryed up to be Miniſters of the Goſpel, Miniſters of the Goſpel: and if the Lord move any to cry againſt them, they are Stocked, or beaten, or priſoned; as in the North-Jayls 23 in priſon now; and many which be priſoners at <hi>Kendal,</hi> as Captain <hi>Ward, Thomas Robertſon,</hi> and widow <hi>Garner,</hi> which hath many ſmall children, which ſuffer becauſe they cannot pay Tythes; and many others which be in <hi>Kendal-</hi>priſon, which were moved of the Lord to ſpeak to the Prieſt, whereof one was moved to ſit in ſackcloth, with aſhes upon her head, and others which have been moved to go in ſackcloth, A Lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the miſerable condition of this Nation, for to ſee ſo much crying up of preaching of the Goſpel, and ſee ſo much Strife and debate, and Oathes, and diſſention among people. But where the Goſpel is, Strife and contention is ceaſed, and oppreſſion taken off. But Oh the Land mourns with this op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing Miniſtery, which hath not entred into the ears of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:183683:12"/> the Magiſtrates. But now is the cry of the people entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ears of the Lord of Sabboth, who will now be avenged of all his adverſaries. And all you unjuſt Law-givers, and unjuſt Judges, to that in all your Conſciences I ſpeak, to be cleared when you are judged by the juſt Judge, the God of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and earth, whoſe terrour is going out, and will go out, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all the ungodly. And you have given them a Law to take Tythes; but they have no Law from God: and they have no Store-houſes; and we ſee that both Strangers, fatherleſs, and widows are wandring abroad, and begging abroad; which the Prieſts that had a command from God, and did takes Tythes according to the Law, did fill ſuch.</p>
            <p>And ſo we ſee that both ye and the Prieſts are contrary to the Scripture; and they neither are true Prieſts under the Law, nor Miniſters of the Goſpel: for their practice is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to theſe Prieſts; which was changeable, which received Tythes, which was a Figure of Jeſus Chriſt the everlaſting Prieſt, who miniſters out of the everlaſting treaſure. Him we witneſs. If we ſhould hold up the Prieſthood which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Tythes, we ſhould deny him come in the fleſh, as all the world doth who receive Tythes; and them that take it. So, who preach the Goſpel, deny the Prieſts which receive Tythes; and who preach the new Covenant, deny the Prieſts that received Tythes according to the Law; and who preach the new Teſtament, deny the Prieſthood that receive Tythes; and who preach the everlaſting Prieſt, denies the changeable Prieſts, that received Tythes, and had a Store-houſe, which were changeable things, and witneſs the unchangeable Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and the everlaſting Treaſure.</p>
            <p>And they which had the Store-houſe in <hi>Moſes</hi> Law, they were to fill it, and the Lord opened the windows of heaven, that there might be meat in his houſe, to fill the widows, to fill the fatherleſs, and to fill the ſtrangers, that there might be no begger in <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was in the firſt Prieſthood in the Law; and they had a command; and they that did not bring
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:183683:12"/> their Tythes, you do not read that they made them pay treble damages. And theſe things were but to ſerve in their places, Figures and Shadows, which were changeable of Him who changeth not, JESUS CHRIST, who is a Prieſt made with an Oath, which theſe are not.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:183683:13"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:183683:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
